<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
<channel>
    <title>arXiv Paper Filter</title>
    <link>https://github.com/None/arxiv_filter</link>
    <description>根据研究兴趣筛选的arXiv论文</description>
    <atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/None/arxiv_filter/main/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>zh-CN</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 12:40:04 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>None@github.com</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 12:40:04 +0800</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
        <day>Saturday</day>
        <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>

    <item>
        <title>Debunk and Infer: Multimodal Fake News Detection via Diffusion-Generated Evidence and LLM Reasoning</title>
        <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21557</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:oai:arXiv.org:2506.21557v1</guid>
        <category>我关注的研究话题是多模态大模型，尤其是与结构化数据（图、序列等）相关的研究，包括大模型结构化数据特征对齐、大模型结构化数据RAG、大模型思维链。具体的研究问题有：（1）如何有效地将结构化的信息（图、序列数据）与自然语言的语义空间进行对齐，使得模型能够同时理解数据结构和语义信息；（2）如何用适当的指令使得大模型理解结构化数据中的结构信息；（3）如何赋予大语言模型图学习下游任务的逐步推理能力，从而逐步推断出更复杂的关系和属性。（4）对于下游任务的推理能力，目前的研究比较少，针对序列数据的推理能力研究非常少。</category>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
        <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
        <dc:creator>Kaiying Yan, Moyang Liu, Yukun Liu, Ruibo Fu, Zhengqi Wen, Jianhua Tao, Xuefei Liu</dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            背景：虚假新闻在多媒体平台的快速传播对信息可信度构成挑战。方法：提出Debunk-and-Infer框架（DIFND），将条件扩散模型的生成能力与多模态大语言模型的协作推理能力相结合，用debunk diffusion生成证据，采用链反驳策略让多智能体MLLM系统生成推理内容和判断结果。效果：在FakeSV和FVC数据集上实验表明，DIFND显著提高检测准确率，优于现有方法，且决策更可靠。
            arXiv:2506.21557v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid spread of fake news across multimedia platforms presents serious challenges to information credibility. In this paper, we propose a Debunk-and-Infer framework for Fake News Detection(DIFND) that leverages debunking knowledge to enhance both the performance and interpretability of fake news detection. DIFND integrates the generative strength of conditional diffusion models with the collaborative reasoning capabilities of multimodal large language models (MLLMs). Specifically, debunk diffusion is employed to generate refuting or authenticating evidence based on the multimodal content of news videos, enriching the evaluation process with diverse yet semantically aligned synthetic samples. To improve inference, we propose a chain-of-debunk strategy where a multi-agent MLLM system produces logic-grounded, multimodal-aware reasoning content and final veracity judgment. By jointly modeling multimodal features, generative debunking cues, and reasoning-rich verification within a unified architecture, DIFND achieves notable improvements in detection accuracy. Extensive experiments on the FakeSV and FVC datasets show that DIFND not only outperforms existing approaches but also delivers trustworthy decisions.
        ]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Instruction Learning Paradigms: A Dual Perspective on White-box and Black-box LLMs</title>
        <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21573</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:oai:arXiv.org:2506.21573v1</guid>
        <category>我关注的研究话题是多模态大模型，尤其是与结构化数据（图、序列等）相关的研究，包括大模型结构化数据特征对齐、大模型结构化数据RAG、大模型思维链。具体的研究问题有：（1）如何有效地将结构化的信息（图、序列数据）与自然语言的语义空间进行对齐，使得模型能够同时理解数据结构和语义信息；（2）如何用适当的指令使得大模型理解结构化数据中的结构信息；（3）如何赋予大语言模型图学习下游任务的逐步推理能力，从而逐步推断出更复杂的关系和属性。（4）对于下游任务的推理能力，目前的研究比较少，针对序列数据的推理能力研究非常少。</category>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
        <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
        <dc:creator>Yanwei Ren, Liu Liu, Baosheng Yu, Jiayan Qiu, Quan Chen</dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            优化大语言模型的指令对发挥其在复杂多样任务中的潜力至关重要，但白盒方法需大量计算资源且表征能力有限，黑盒模型成本高昂。为此，研究提出新框架融合二者优势，黑盒模型提供高质量多样的指令初始化，白盒模型通过隐藏状态和输出特征提供细粒度可解释性，通过语义相似性约束融合成统一高维表征以迭代优化指令。经多任务评估，该方法优于现有基线，为大模型应用提供可扩展高效方案。
            arXiv:2506.21573v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optimizing instructions for large language models (LLMs) is critical for harnessing their full potential in complex and diverse tasks. However, relying solely on white-box approaches demands extensive computational resources and offers limited representational capacity, while black-box models can incur prohibitive financial costs. To address these challenges, we introduce a novel framework that seamlessly merges the strengths of both paradigms. Black-box models provide high-quality, diverse instruction initializations, and white-box models supply fine-grained interpretability through hidden states and output features. By enforcing a semantic similarity constraint, these components fuse into a unified high-dimensional representation that captures deep semantic and structural nuances, enabling an iterative optimization process to refine instruction quality and adaptability. Extensive evaluations across a broad spectrum of tasks-ranging from complex reasoning to cross-lingual generalization-demonstrate that our approach consistently outperforms state-of-the-art baselines. This fusion of black-box initialization with advanced semantic refinement yields a scalable and efficient solution, paving the way for next-generation LLM-driven applications in diverse real-world scenarios. The source code will be released soon.
        ]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Structured Attention Matters to Multimodal LLMs in Document Understanding</title>
        <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21600</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:oai:arXiv.org:2506.21600v1</guid>
        <category>我关注的研究话题是多模态大模型，尤其是与结构化数据（图、序列等）相关的研究，包括大模型结构化数据特征对齐、大模型结构化数据RAG、大模型思维链。具体的研究问题有：（1）如何有效地将结构化的信息（图、序列数据）与自然语言的语义空间进行对齐，使得模型能够同时理解数据结构和语义信息；（2）如何用适当的指令使得大模型理解结构化数据中的结构信息；（3）如何赋予大语言模型图学习下游任务的逐步推理能力，从而逐步推断出更复杂的关系和属性。（4）对于下游任务的推理能力，目前的研究比较少，针对序列数据的推理能力研究非常少。</category>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
        <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
        <dc:creator>Chang Liu, Hongkai Chen, Yujun Cai, Hang Wu, Qingwen Ye, Ming-Hsuan Yang, Yiwei Wang</dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            文档理解对多模态大语言模型是重大挑战。以往研究多关注精准多模态查询定位证据页，该研究聚焦输入格式对文档理解性能的影响。经分析发现，原始OCR文本会削弱模型性能，原因是注意力分散和结构丢失。为此，提出用LaTex范式编码文档元素的保结构方法，保持文档层次和空间关系。注意力分析表明，结构化文本能引导模型关注语义区域，减少注意力浪费，显著提升多模态大语言模型在不同文档类型上的问答性能，且无需架构修改和额外训练。
            arXiv:2506.21600v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Document understanding remains a significant challenge for multimodal large language models (MLLMs). While previous research has primarily focused on locating evidence pages through precise multimodal queries, our work investigates a fundamental yet overlooked aspect: how input format influences document comprehension performance. Through systematic analysis, we discover that raw OCR text often impairs rather than improves MLLMs' performance, which is a counterintuitive finding we attribute to attention dispersion and structure loss. To further substantiate our hypothesis, we propose a novel structure-preserving approach that encodes document elements using the LaTex paradigm, maintaining the hierarchical organization and spatial relationships critical for comprehension. Our attention analysis reveals that structured text induces structured attention patterns on both textual and visual content, directing models to focus on semantically meaningful regions while reducing attention waste. This approach significantly enhances MLLMs' document question answering performance across diverse document types without requiring architectural modifications or additional training.
        ]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>REDELEX: A Framework for Relational Deep Learning Exploration</title>
        <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22199</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:oai:arXiv.org:2506.22199v1</guid>
        <category>我关注的研究话题是多模态大模型，尤其是与结构化数据（图、序列等）相关的研究，包括大模型结构化数据特征对齐、大模型结构化数据RAG、大模型思维链。具体的研究问题有：（1）如何有效地将结构化的信息（图、序列数据）与自然语言的语义空间进行对齐，使得模型能够同时理解数据结构和语义信息；（2）如何用适当的指令使得大模型理解结构化数据中的结构信息；（3）如何赋予大语言模型图学习下游任务的逐步推理能力，从而逐步推断出更复杂的关系和属性。（4）对于下游任务的推理能力，目前的研究比较少，针对序列数据的推理能力研究非常少。</category>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
        <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
        <dc:creator>Jakub Pele\v{s}ka, Gustav \v{S}\'ir</dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            背景：关系数据库是存储结构化信息的常用方式，关系深度学习（RDL）将其视为图结构处理预测任务，但缺乏对不同RDL模型性能与数据库特征关系的分析。方法：提出REDELEX框架，在70多个关系数据库上评估不同复杂度的RDL模型，并与经典方法对比。效果：证实RDL总体性能更优，还揭示了影响性能的主要因素，如模型复杂度、数据库大小和结构属性。
            arXiv:2506.22199v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Relational databases (RDBs) are widely regarded as the gold standard for storing structured information. Consequently, predictive tasks leveraging this data format hold significant application promise. Recently, Relational Deep Learning (RDL) has emerged as a novel paradigm wherein RDBs are conceptualized as graph structures, enabling the application of various graph neural architectures to effectively address these tasks. However, given its novelty, there is a lack of analysis into the relationships between the performance of various RDL models and the characteristics of the underlying RDBs.
  In this study, we present REDELEX$-$a comprehensive exploration framework for evaluating RDL models of varying complexity on the most diverse collection of over 70 RDBs, which we make available to the community. Benchmarked alongside key representatives of classic methods, we confirm the generally superior performance of RDL while providing insights into the main factors shaping performance, including model complexity, database sizes and their structural properties.
        ]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Exploiting Vision Language Model for Training-Free 3D Point Cloud OOD Detection via Graph Score Propagation</title>
        <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22375</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:oai:arXiv.org:2506.22375v1</guid>
        <category>我关注的研究话题是多模态大模型，尤其是与结构化数据（图、序列等）相关的研究，包括大模型结构化数据特征对齐、大模型结构化数据RAG、大模型思维链。具体的研究问题有：（1）如何有效地将结构化的信息（图、序列数据）与自然语言的语义空间进行对齐，使得模型能够同时理解数据结构和语义信息；（2）如何用适当的指令使得大模型理解结构化数据中的结构信息；（3）如何赋予大语言模型图学习下游任务的逐步推理能力，从而逐步推断出更复杂的关系和属性。（4）对于下游任务的推理能力，目前的研究比较少，针对序列数据的推理能力研究非常少。</category>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
        <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
        <dc:creator>Tiankai Chen, Yushu Li, Adam Goodge, Fei Teng, Xulei Yang, Tianrui Li, Xun Xu</dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            这是一篇关于3D点云数据分布外（OOD）检测的研究。现有2D图像数据OOD检测方法拓展到3D环境存在障碍。该研究提出无训练框架，利用视觉语言模型（VLM）进行3D点云OOD检测。通过构建基于类原型和测试数据的图，利用数据流形结构提升VLM检测效果，提出图分数传播（GSP）方法，结合提示聚类和自训练负提示改进OOD评分。该方法适用于少样本场景，在合成和真实数据集上均优于现有方法。
            arXiv:2506.22375v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Out-of-distribution (OOD) detection in 3D point cloud data remains a challenge, particularly in applications where safe and robust perception is critical. While existing OOD detection methods have shown progress for 2D image data, extending these to 3D environments involves unique obstacles. This paper introduces a training-free framework that leverages Vision-Language Models (VLMs) for effective OOD detection in 3D point clouds. By constructing a graph based on class prototypes and testing data, we exploit the data manifold structure to enhancing the effectiveness of VLMs for 3D OOD detection. We propose a novel Graph Score Propagation (GSP) method that incorporates prompt clustering and self-training negative prompting to improve OOD scoring with VLM. Our method is also adaptable to few-shot scenarios, providing options for practical applications. We demonstrate that GSP consistently outperforms state-of-the-art methods across synthetic and real-world datasets 3D point cloud OOD detection.
        ]]></description>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>